<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: IR | CCI]]></title>
  <link href="http://TakahiroHaruyama.github.io/blog/categories/ir/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://TakahiroHaruyama.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-22T11:10:09+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://TakahiroHaruyama.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Takahiro Haruyama (@cci_forensics)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ID/IDAPython scripts extracting PlugX configs]]></title>
    <link href="http://TakahiroHaruyama.github.io/blog/2014/03/27/id-slash-idapython-scripts-extracting-plugx-configs/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T00:00:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://TakahiroHaruyama.github.io/blog/2014/03/27/id-slash-idapython-scripts-extracting-plugx-configs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I release Immunity Debugger and IDAPython scirpts dumping PlugX configs (and original PEs) then parsing them.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>IIJ-SECT (CSIRT team at IIJ, Inc.) classifies PlugX samples into 3 types: type I/II/III. In more detail, check <a href="https://www.blackhat.com/asia-14/briefings.html#Haruyama">our presentation</a>.
The Immunity Debugger script can be used for PlugX type I&amp;II. The IDAPython script can parse type III configs.</p>

<h3>Distinction between Type I&amp;II and III</h3>

<p>Before using the scripts, we should guess which type the PlugX specimen is. Generally, type I/II injects their codes twice: the 1st target process defined in the config and msiexec. The 1st target process may be svchost/msiexec/iexplore/winlogon like the following figures. However, some samples don&rsquo;t inject according to the config (stand-alone flag), additionally, other several specimens inject only once. So, the criteria is ambiguous. Moreover, in my experience, Type III is usually executed by rundll32.</p>

<p><img src="/images/post/plugx_scripts/type_diff_process.PNG" alt="type_diff_process" /></p>

<h3>ID Script for Type I&amp;II</h3>

<p>We need to copy the ID script into PyCommands folder in advance. Then we attach to one of injected processes. After attaching to the process, run the script (!plugx_dumper). If successful, the parsed config is displayed in Log View. The result and decompressed original PE file are saved in the same folder.</p>

<p><img src="/images/post/plugx_scripts/ID_result.PNG" alt="ID_result" /></p>

<p>If the following message is output, the specimen may be neither type I nor II.</p>

<p><img src="/images/post/plugx_scripts/ID_failed.png" alt="ID_failed" /></p>

<h3>IDAPython Script for Type III</h3>

<p>Since type III variants are more obfuscated (e.g., massive obfuscated strings, inserted random junk codes), it&rsquo;s difficult to extract the config from process memory. Therefore, I wrote an IDAPython script for parsing type III configs.</p>

<p>To use the script, we must find the function to decode obfuscated strings and set it as decode_function_name in the script. It may be an obstacle for DFIR people not reverse-engineering malware.</p>

<p><img src="/images/post/plugx_scripts/IDA_prepare.PNG" alt="IDA_prepare" /></p>

<p>After the configuration, run the script. We can check the result in Output window. Parsed config information is saved as &ldquo;config.txt&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img src="/images/post/plugx_scripts/IDA_result.PNG" alt="IDA_result" /></p>

<h3>Note: Demo Version</h3>

<p>PlugX demo specimens (some demo samples pop-up &ldquo;THIS IS A DEMO VERSION!!!&rdquo;, others not) do not include config data. When detecting the specimen is demo version, the scripts notify us of the result like this. The configs are filled by &ldquo;XXXX&rdquo; in demo samples.</p>

<p><img src="/images/post/plugx_scripts/Demos.PNG" alt="Demos" /></p>

<h3>Download</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="/downloads/scripts/plugx_dumper.py">Immunity Debugger script for type I&amp;II</a> (Supported config sizes are 0x150C/0x1510/0x1B18/0x1D18/0x2540/0x7AC#2)</li>
<li><a href="/downloads/scripts/plugx_config_dumper_IDA.py">IDAPython script for type III</a> (Supported config sizes are 0x72C/0x76C/0xDF0/0x7AC/0x840)</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>2014/4/2 updated</strong></p>

<p>Immunity Debugger script output improved and 0x7AC#2 config added, that is different from Type III 0x7AC (thanks to You Nakatsuru/Arai)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
